Guide to the Civil Rights Movement and Wayside Theatre photographs, 1960s RL.11723
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Civil Rights Movement and Wayside Theatre photographs
1960s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lyon, Danny
RL.11723
0.2 Linear Feet 1 box 18 prints
Collection comprises 18 black-and-white photographs taken in the 1960s, assembled by a private collector and organized into two distinct groups: nine journalistic photographs documenting civil rights movement events, some credited to Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) photographers Cliff Vaughs, Danny Lyon, and Rufus Hinton, with others unattributed; and nine prints of an unidentified multi-racial dramatic performance, circa mid-1960s, found in the archives of the Wayside Theatre in Middletown, Virginia. The Civil Rights prints typically include detailed press captions on the backs, and include images of injured and jailed demonstrators, police, bombed-out churches, and portraits of activists Fannie Lou Hamer and Atlanta's Markham Street rent protest leader Willie Williams. All the prints except one measure roughly 8x10 inches. Acquired as part of the John Hope Research Center for African and African American History and Culture at Duke University.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Civil Rights Movement and Wayside Theater photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Content Description
Collection comprises 18 black-and-white photographs taken in the 1960s, assembled by a private collector and organized into two distinct groups: nine journalistic photographs documenting civil rights movement events, some credited to Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) photographers Cliff Vaughs, Danny Lyon, and Rufus Hinton, with others unattributed; and nine prints of an unidentified multi-racial staged production.
The Civil Rights prints typically feature detailed press captions on the backs, and include images of bombed-out churches, injured and jailed demonstrators, police, and portraits of activist Fannie Lou Hamer and Atlanta's Markham Street housing protest leader Willie Williams. Some prints also bear a SNCC photo credit stamp with the organization's Atlanta address.
The second group consists of two contact sheets and seven prints showing an unidentified multi-racial dramatic or musical performance perhaps staged by the Wayside Theatre in Middletown, Virginia, or may possibly be related to the Garrick Players in Washington, D.C. or to the Free Southern Theater founded by SNCC. The time period appears to be the early 1960s.
All the prints except one are roughly 8x10 inches.
Acquired as part of the John Hope Research Center for African and African American History and Culture at Duke University.
Actors -- Photographs; African American photographers -- United States; African Americans -- Civil rights -- Press coverage; Civil rights demonstrations -- Photographs; Civil rights movements -- Southern States -- Photographs; Civil rights movements -- Southern States -- History -- 20th century; Community theater; Documentary Photography -- Southern States; Photojournalism -- Southern States; Race relations -- Drama; Alabama -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Georgia -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Mississippi -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Southern States -- Race relations -- History -- 20th century; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.); Hinton, Rufus; Lyon, Danny; Vaughs, Cliff, 1937-2016
- Civil Rights Movement, 1960s
  Scope and Contents
  Titles are derived from original titles or captions found on the backs of the prints. Almost all the prints are attributed to SNCC photographers.
  - Mrs. Fannie Lou Hamer, taken by Cliff Vaughs, 1967; 10 x 8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11723-P-0001)
    Close-up side view of Fannie Lou Hamer at an unidentified event, seated, holding an American flag, and listening. Taken by SNCC photographer Cliff Vaughs. Stamped on retro with SNCC photo credit and address. Date taken from same image found online.
  - Injured African American woman with bandaged head sitting at Winslow Hospital in Danville, Virginia, 1963 June; 10 x 8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11723-P-0002)
    Caption pasted on the back reads: "Danville, VA., June 1963 --- One of 47 peaceful demonstrators hospitalized on the night of June 10 after being beaten by police. SNCC photo taken at Winslow Hospital, Danville, following prayer vigil at the city jail where high pressure fire hoses were turned on the demonstrators, who were then beaten with billy sticks by the police." Unidentified photographer.
  - Police and crowd gather on a street in front of a house, 1960s; 8 1/8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11723-P-0003)
    Photograph lacks caption or other information.
  - Markham Street rent strike leader Willie Williams, taken by Rufus Hinton, 1966 March 6; 10 x 8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11723-P-0004)
    General
    Caption on the back of the photographs reads: "Markham Street rent strike leader Willie Williams holds frozen rat locked out of his house in the background Williams is camping on the sidewalk." Stamped on back with SNCC photo credit and address.
    This photograph was taken by Rufus Hinton, a SNCC photographer who, at one point, was responsible for documenting Georgia, Florida, North Carolina, and South Carolina.
  - Two demonstrators on a sidewalk hold up signs, after 1965?; 10 x 8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11723-P-0005)
    This image by an unknown photographer is of two men, one black, one white holding signs; the most prominently-figured protestor is holding a sign that reads: "My brother was beaten in Selma while the FBI watched." The other sign reads, "Justice in Selma."
  - Philadelphia, Mississippi -- Choctaw Indian Church, after 1964 September 18; 5 x 7 inch print mounted on sheet of 8 x 8 1/2 paper. (Box 1, Image RL.11723-P-0006)
    Unknown photographer. The caption for this photograph reads: "Philadelphia, Mississippi -- Choctaw Indian Church. On September 18, 1964, this Mennonite church which served the Coy community of Choctaw Indians, and which had a white pastor, was severly damaged. The building is located thirteen miles from Philadelphia on Route 21, in Neshoba County, Mississippi."
  - Group of 14 African American girls standing in a cell in a Leesburg, Georgia jail, taken by Danny Lyon, 1963 September; 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11723-P-0007)
    The caption pasted on the back reads: "SNCC photo taken at the Leesburg, Georgia stockade in Sept. 1963, where 20 girls, 11 to 15 years old were held for as long as one month in a cell 8' x 10' x 30'. They had no beds, springs, mattresses or blankets. They were arrested in August 1963, at various times, in connection with peaceful demonstrations in Americus, Georgia. SNCC photo." No photographer's name is present.
    Taken by Magnum photographer Danny Lyon (image credited in other institutional collections).
  - Society Hill Baptist Church, McComb, Mississippi, bombed Sept 20, 1964, taken by Cliff Vaughs, after September 20, 1964; 10 x 8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11723-P-0008)
    Title appears handwritten on back of photograph. Stamped on back with SNCC photo credit and address.
  - Bombed Freedom House -- Vicksburg, Mississippi, Sept, 1964 -- SNCC photo by Cliff Vaughs, 1964 September; 10 x 8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11723-P-0009)
    Title from handwritten caption on back. The photographer was Clifford Vaughs, who, at one point, was a staff photographer for SNCC.
- Wayside Theatre, Early 1960s?; 9 items 2 contact sheets; 7 prints
  The origins and setting of these unmarked prints are unknown, as is the photographer. They were discovered in a file cabinet at the Wayside Theatre in the small city of Middletown, Virginia, close to Washington D.C., which was a cinema built in the 1940s before its transformation in 1962 into a small community theater. It closed in 2013.
  The seven glossy black-and-white photographs, all 8 1/8 x 10 inches, and two 8x10 contact sheets show groups of African American and white actors in the middle of an unnamed dramatic production. It seems to have included music; one of the actors holds a tambourine and actors appear to be singing. In some scenes the setting appears to be a church.
  The performance may have been staged by the Wayside Theatre or possibly by the Garrick Players, the former home of the director of the Wayside Theatre; or it may be a Free Southern Theater production in Washington D.C. or some other locality. Judging by dress and haircuts, the date appears to be the early to mid 1960s.
  - Contact sheet depicting scenes from a production (Box 1, Print RL.11723-P-0010)
  - Contact sheet depicting scenes from a production (Box 1, Print RL.11723-P-0011)
  - An actor stands at a podium on stage (Box 1, Print RL.11723-P-0012)
    An actor stands at a podium on stage while three other actors look on during a production at the Wayside Theater in Middletown, Virginia(?).
    The theater was formerly a cinema house.
  - Actors on stage (Box 1, Print RL.11723-P-0013)
    In this photo, a woman stands at the front of the stage, while a man holding a tambourine and a larger group of people occupy the background.
    The theater was formerly a cinema house and is now closed.
  - Actors on stage (Box 1, Print RL.11723-P-0014)
    A large group of actors appear on stage, clapping, during a production at the Wayside Theater in Middletown, Virginia(?).
  - Actors on stage (Box 1, Print RL.11723-P-0015)
    Four actors--two women in the sitting in the front, two men standing behind them--appear on stage during a production at the Wayside Theater in Middletown, Virginia.
  - Actors on stage (Box 1, Print RL.11723-P-0016)
    An actor holds a tambourine while other actors in the background look around during a production at the Wayside Theater in Middletown, Virginia(?).
  - Actors on stage (Box 1, Print RL.11723-P-0017)
    Four actors on stage, one waving a tambourine, during a production at the Wayside Theater in Middletown, Virginia(?).
  - Actors on stage (Box 1, Print RL.11723-P-0018)
    A large group of actors appear to be clapping and singing during a production at the Wayside Theater in Middletown, Virginia(?).